Today's דף Daf is ל', Lamed, but we are
picking up on כ"ט עמוד ב' Kaf Tet Amud Bet at the
very top. Exactly at the... we are doing on the משנה Mishnah
that speaks about פרשיות parshiyot of the מזוזה מעכבת, mezuzah ma'akevet, but
the משנה Mishnah said even one letter, so we're talking about what
does that mean one letter? Because you take for granted that if
one letter is missing it's no good, and this is to tell
you some of the very specific requirements, for example, there's a requirement
called מוקף גויל, mukaf gvil, that it have to be surrounded by
parchment. It cannot be connected to the letters nearby. Also,
so for that the גמרא Gemara says, however, that's sort of the
outer perimeter of the letter, if there's a hole smack in the
middle of the ה', Hei, so that the little leg of the
ה', Hei, you know, the two inner legs, are not touching parchment,
they're touching the hole, that's כשר, kasher, because מוקף גויל mukaf gvil
is about the area around it. And then it said that what
about if some of the letter is broken? So like it says
like the leg, the outer leg of the ה' Hei is actually
broken or even the inner like, you know, the inner little leg,
but it's not just that it's touching a hole, it's that it's
not actually a full line. So the גמרא Gemara says it has
to look like an אות קטנה, ot ktana, a smallest letter which
means like a י'. Yud. There's actually some debate, the ראש Rosh
says that they're talking about the sort of, you know, the large
leg of the ה', Hei, the right leg. That have to look
like the י', Yud, but if the inner leg is enough that
it's even a tiny little dot, that's what the ראש Rosh says.
Many other ראשונים Rishonim say that even the inner leg has to
at least be the size of the י'. Yud.
Did I say size of י'?
Yud? Size of י'? Yud?
Yeah, but it depends about how big is your י', Yud, but
okay, but of the same font I assume is the point.
Okay, טוב.
tov. And we're up to...
so the גמרא Gemara had that discussion, we're going to continue with
some of those issues. And again, the point is other than the
גמרא Gemara we saw that the קוצו של י', kotzo shel yud,
which again might mean the red leg, the right leg which is
obvious, or might mean
the... no, in general the גמרא Gemara does not give very much
in terms of the exact details of what a letter has to
look like. It's more you have to look like the letter, what
we are familiar with the letter, we're about to see in a
minute about even asking a small boy to, you know, recognize it.
Nevertheless, there are other criteria like it had to be surrounded with
גויל, gvil, it has to, you know, if it's cut short, it's
not going down the full length, at what stage is that still
considered the letter and so on. But there's not like a big
table
if you look in the משנה
ברורה Mishnah
Berurah
there on הלכות תפילין, Hilchot Tefillin, you will see that he sort
of goes letter by letter and believe me if you are learning
from a סופר sofer you'll see even more. So he actually here,
you know, goes highlights this whole thing about, you know, every single
letter, this is in סימן ל"ו, siman lamed vav, you know, here's
what an א' Aleph has to look like, here's what a ב'
Bet has to look like, here's what a ג' Gimmel has to
look like. Of course it's a little hard without pictures, there actually
I thought was some pictures somewhere in the back with this. But
anyway,
but regardless,
the גמרא Gemara does not give you most of, yeah well that's
the גמרא Gemara and תוספות. Tosafot. The גמרא Gemara did not give
you most of those details. So let's keep looking, one interesting one
was this idea of the קוץ kotz of the י'. Yud. So
now four lines from the top on
כ"ט עמוד ב'. kaf tet amud bet. רמי בר חמרי דהוא חמוא
דרמי בר דיקולי, Rami bar Chamri dehu chamua de-Rami bar Dikuli, רמי
Rami of Chamri which means of course dates, who is the father-in-law
of רמי Rami the son of דיקולי Dikuli which of course means
a date palm. So
I wonder if their names had anything to do with marrying into
the family or maybe it was
once he married into the family he changed his name I don't
know. Anyway, איפסיקא כרעא דוי"ו,
ifsika
karda d'vav, so the leg of the וי"ו vav was broken in
the word of ויהרג va-yeharej which is in the פסוק pasuk of
one of the four פרשיות parshiyot of תפילין. Tefillin. It says you
know God smote all of the firstborn. So
ויהרג, va-yeharej, ויהרג, va-yeharog, let me see, right, maybe it's ויהרג. va-yeharog.
Okay anyway בנקבה, binikva,
with a hole. אתא לקמיה דרבי זירא, ata lekamei de-Rabbi Zeira, he
came to Rabbi Zeira. אמר ליה זיל אייתי ינוקא דלא חכים ולא
טיפש, amar lei zil ayiti yanuka delo chakim velo tipesh,
go get a child that's not too smart and not too dumb,
average intelligence, right? Not too smart because you don't want him to
figure out by context what the word is and it's not really
just by what the letters look like and not too dumb because
you want him to have a sense of what the letters should
look like, okay. אי קרי ליה ויהרג כשר, ikari lei va-yeharog kasher,
if he read it like it should be it's כשר, kasher, אלא,
elo, if he doesn't read it that way then ויהריהו ve-yeharehu with
two י' yuds presumably ופסול. u-pasul. The וי"ו vav would be like
a י' Yud and it would be invalid. Now this is specifically
with the issue that the leg of the וי"ו vav might not
be long enough and is it a וי"ו vav is it a
י'? Yud? There are other types of things which are clear formal
invalidities and then it doesn't matter what it looks like. If it's
not מוקף גויל, mukaf gvil, if it's touching of neighboring letter I
don't care what a little boy, you know, says about what it
looks like, that's what it looks like, it's touching another letter. But
if there's a question about well is this long enough to be
considered a וי"ו vav or maybe it's so small it's a י',
Yud, a lot of that has to do with what does it
look like. So I'll just leave you this is a major area
of הלכה, halacha, you know sometimes this will happen there'll be some
question in the שול shul and they'll bring up some little kid
that boy could be a girl sometimes they they block out... the
surrounding words or letters so shouldn't be influenced by interpreting it by
context. Okay? But the big
question is, what types of things is it just a question of
does it look like it? that you want to get sort of
an innocent opinion of whether it looks like it, and what types
of things are possible formal invalidities. So I just want to read
you very briefly, we're not going to have that full discussion now,
but just to give you a little bit of sense, I want
to read to you how this is ruled in the שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, this this same הלכה halakha about getting a minor to
come in and read it.
Wait, by a minor it could be someone who doesn't have a
bunch of education? Oh right, that's true.
Yes, that is correct.
Okay, so because like this, נפסק אחת
מהאותיות, nifsak achat me'ha'otiyot,
if one of the letters is broken, and the רמ״א Rama says
הפשוטות, hapishutot,
which is like basically like a straight thing like a ו vav
or a ז zayin or or what? Yeah, like it's like a,
yeah, meaning it doesn't have to be a hole, it could just
be like the ink broke and it's not a straight line of
ink. Okay, אם תינוק שאינו לא חכים ולא טיפש שיודע לקרוא, im
tinok she'eino lo chakim v'lo tipeish she'yodea likro, so if it's read
by a minor like this, אם לאו פסול, im lav pasul, and
then he says ואין צריך לכסות לו שאר אותיות כמו שנוהגין, v'ein
tzarich lechasos lo shear otiyot kemo she'nohagin, you don't have to cover
up the other letters although that's the practice, you don't really have
to do that. Okay, and then the רמ״א Rama says, מיהו אם
אנו רואין שלא ניכר צורת האות כתיקונו פסול אף על פי שתינוק
קורא אותו כאותו התו. mihu im anu ro'in shelo nikar tzurat ha'ot
ketikuno pasul af al pi she'tinok korei oto ke'oto ha'tav. If we
see that it doesn't look officially like the letter, even if the
child can identify it, it's not good. Okay, and so again you
see this tension between is there a formal rule or is it
about what does it look like? So we're saying well if they're
not sure get a child, but if we know it's not the
letter, how do we know?
And then it says high what everyone says? סופר? Sopher? Yeah, yeah.
There's two lines of שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and this amount of
commentary on דף על הדף. daf al ha'daf. All right. So what
was in that?
That was, you know, it's a range and judgment call. Right.
There's a certain point where even if he guesses it right,
oh the question is is he guessing or is he identifying? So
maybe that's what the רמ״א Rama means, it was a good guess
but we know that it's not really. You know what? It's no
other letter, got to be this, looks closest to this.
If it's formal, I mean, I'm already thinking, you know, which which
parent is going to be happy that their child was chosen as
the average?
All right.
Anyway,
then one more law in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, one more
law he says, הדא דמכשירינן כשנפסקה אות דוקא כשנכתב בכשרות ואחר כך
נפסק. hada d'makhshirin nan keshenifskah ot davka kshe'nikhtav b'khashrut v'achar kach nifsak.
This is when it was originally written kosher and then either some,
there was a hole or the ink broke or something afterwards. אבל
אם מתחילה כשנכתב היה שם נקב ונפסק בו או אם רגל הקוף
כפופה כיוצא בו מגוויל או טובה כלפי הקיף כלפי מתחילתו
פסול. aval im mitkhila kshe'nikhtav haya sham nekev v'nifsak bo o im
regal ha'kof kfufa k'yotze bo migvil o tovah klapi he'ekef klapi mitkhilato
pasul. Now this is a problem about מוקף גוויל, mukaf gvil, because
here he's talking about there's a hole. So the hole is only
okay if it was afterwards, but if the hole was there beforehand,
then it would never have been מוקף גוויל mukaf gvil because the
end of the ink would have been touching a hole and not
touching קלף. klaf. Okay, so you have to make sure it was
written originally correctly and it was מוקף גוויל, mukaf gvil, then a
hole came, is it still the letter? Let's get a minor to
check, but we have to make we have to double check what
the minor is saying and make sure you know that it really,
if it can be considered the letter. Very famous area of הלכה.
halakha. That was in Engel where
they had to close five Torahs in one morning?
Oh my gosh. Five. Wow. Okay. That's probably a פרוץ protz בעל
קורא baal korei knew too much. I there was a I was
once,
they didn't call it Balga.
Interesting, and I think there were six Torahs.
I knew I knew of a guy that they would never give
him an עליה aliyah because every time they give him an עליה
aliyah he'd find a פסול p'sul in the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
so finally it was like after a year he didn't have an
עליה, aliyah, so they had רחמנות rachmanus and they gave him הגבהה.
hagbah. So as he's doing הגבהה hagbah he says, oh I see...
All right. Anyway, so גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, Rav Yehuda says in
the name of Rav. So now we talked before about Moshe's difficulty
with the מנורה, menorah, now we get one of the most famous
גמרות Gemaras which is also a מדרש midrash in שבת, Shabbat, an
אגדתא aggadata in שבת. Shabbat. בשעה שעלה משה למרום, Besha'ah she'alah Moshe
l'marom, when
Moshe went up to the heavens to get the תורה, Torah, מצאו
להקדוש ברוך הוא שהיה יושב וקושר כתרים לאותיות. matzo l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu
she'yoshev v'kosher ketarim l'otiyot. He found God tying crowns to the letters.
אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav,
now what are these crowns? We're going to see in a minute,
if you see in the תוספות Tosfos there's a little thing by
the ז, zayin, these are being special little crowns that are put
on the letters of the שעטנז גץ, shaatnez getz, ש ע ט
נ ז ג צ, shin ayin tet nun zayin gimel tzadi,
whether they are the middle letters or the end letters, they get
little three-pointed crowns. There's questions how exactly they're spread out. You see
in תוספות Tosfos one example is one of the actually sticks goes
down, we don't say that all three go up, but they're spread
over the top of the letter. We basically say that the three
little sticks that go up that make the crown all come at
the edge of the letter... like this?
Like
no, not like the
ז... zayin... take a look here...
well a little bit, not but not as spread out as they
are there. This is I wrote a גט, get,
I'm sorry, I didn't get a chance to upload it to the
blog there.
So here are three different... an examples of כתב Ksav and you
can take a look, I don't know why they put this פסוק
Pasuk with שם השם Shem Hashem in here, so this is שמות.
Sheimos. Anyway, you can take a look, the נונין, Noonen, get it?
The נון סופית, Noon Sofit, right? The עינין, Ayenen, get it? The
שינין, Sheenen, the גימלן, Gimmelen, so actually this does is really much
like centered, the עין Ayin is a good example, it's really much
centered in the, the, that, in the middle of the, you know,
the middle top is the high one and then the two one
come sort of close by, not exactly like the תוספות Tosafot that
we have. Okay, so three different examples of כתב, Ksav, but they're
all pretty similar in terms of how they make the, these things
which are called
קרנין.
Karnin.
Yeah, wondering if there's the equivalent to the quick brown fox jumped
over the lazy...
Yeah, I have no idea why they picked this פסוק Pasuk of
all things, especially I would have picked a פסוק Pasuk that didn't
have שם השם Shem Hashem in it. It's not a פסוק Pasuk
in the תורה Torah anyway. Okay, so now let's take a look.
So משה Moshe went up and saw God tying the crowns to
the letters. אמר לפניו, Amar Lefanav, he said to him, רבונו של
עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, Master of the Universe, מי מעכב על ידך,
Mi Me'akev Al Yadecha, who's holding back your hand? Now that's a
very funny phrase. What do you mean holding back his hand? Actually,
his hand isn't being held back, he's tying the, the crowns to
letters. But presumably what it means is who's preventing you from giving
the תורה Torah already? Like, give it already! All the letters are
written, who's stopping you from giving it now? Why do you have
to spend your time putting on these crowns?
אמר לו, Amar Lo, so God said to משה, Moshe, אדם אחד
יש שעתיד להיות בסוף כמה דורות, Adam Echad Yesh She'atid Lihyot Besof
Kama Dorot, there's one person who will be at the end of
many generations, ועקיבא בן יוסף שמו, VeAkiva Ben Yosef Shemo,
his name is עקיבא Akiva the son of יוסף, Yosef, רבי עקיבא,
Rebbi Akiva, שעתיד לדרוש על כל קוץ וקוץ, She'atid Lidrosh Al Kol
Kotz VeKotz,
there you have the קוץ, Kotz, the קוץ Kotz of the יוד,
Yud, who is in the end going to interpret on every little
jot and tittle is how we would say קוץ וקוץ, Kotz VeKotz,
תילי תילין של הלכות, Tillei Tillin Shel Halachot,
mountains and mountains of laws he will learn out from every little
jot and tittle. So that's why עקיבא's Akiva holding me back. I
gotta put on these little crowns so he'll be able to interpret
it. I have to tell you what's fascinating about this. Do we
see עקיבא Akiva that he does it anywhere at the end? Do
we דורש? Doresh? No, he more דורש Dorshes an extra את Es
and a יוד, Yud, not actually the, and that's a good point
because it's a little bit of a problem here. If there were
like a more arbitrary or random assignment of the crowns, you could
say that every crown has something to learn out from it. But
if it's a fixed system, you do it on very specific letters,
then how can you use it as a basis for דראש? Drash?
You know, you can totally predict it. So every גימל's Gimmel going
to get it, every נון's Noon going to get it, so that's
part of the reason why we don't find רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
doing it. So I don't know, there's gotta be a good like
דראש Drash here about like this אגדתא Agadeta about what that means.
Probably what it means and this is I think the major theme
of this, which we're going to see, is the power of the
human creativity and what it means about our partnership in תורה שבעל
פה. Torah SheBaal Peh. That even to a certain degree if the,
you know, if it's not,
it's not intrinsically meaningful. You can't say that every one of the
כתבים Kesavim is intrinsically meaningful because we know where it's going to
appear. Okay, but nevertheless, part of what God does by giving us
over the ability to be part of תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBaal
Peh is that we can infer things even if they're not פשט
Pshat exactly. You know, which are sort of always אשתדלות, Eshtadlus, even
if it's not really what God meant to mean, if I'm gonna
put a little כתר Keser on a גימל, Gimmel, I'm gonna say
that's what it means over here. And that of course was the
power of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. No, I don't know if we
ever find him do it with the כתבים, Kesavim, but that's his
power, that he was able to learn anything out of a, could
be a metaphor. Yeah, exactly. Okay.
When have people...
when they saw it like in the ancient documents?
Oh, that's a very good question, how far back do the, these
קרנין Karnin go?
Yeah, in the בר כוכבא Bar Kochba caves we definitely have that,
although I'll look...
yeah. Oh, no, we have...
no, no, we definitely have.
I'll look it
up, I'll look it up, that's a great question, I don't know.
That's true. We do know, and when we get to learning תפילין,
Tefillin, that there's a debate of רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam about how the פרשיות Parshiyot are ordered in the תפילין, Tefillin,
and both versions were found in... were found in מצדה. Masada. Okay.
But about these things, I'm sure we know, I just don't know
right now.
Would we say if they may appear besides...? It's a good... absolutely.
I'll take a look, I'll take a look.
Technically at the time of סיני Sinai were different, the letters looked
differently.
Correct, correct, which the בבלי Bavli does not acknowledge but the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi does. Okay, so let's keep on going. אמר לפניו, Amar Lefanav,
so he said to him, רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, הראני,
Hareini, show it to me. So
show it to me. אמר לו, Amar Lo, so he said חזור
לאחורך, Chazor Le'achorecha, look... go behind yourself, which is also a suggestive
phrase, but probably means that anyway, צא דורש Tzei Dorshes means turn
around. הלך וישב בסוף שמונה שורות. Halach VeYashav Besof Shmonah Shurot. So
he went into רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva classroom and he sat at
the back of the eight rows. Okay. ולא היה יודע מה הן
אומרים. Velo Hayah Yodea Mah Hen Omrim. So he didn't know what
they were talking about. They were learning הלכה, Halachah, it didn't look
too familiar to him. He thought he knew the תורה, Torah, that's
why he had to be sent to the back of the classroom.
Okay. תשש כחו, Tashash Kocho,
so he felt very weak, he was sort of a little despondent.
כיוון שהגיע לדבר אחד, Keivan Shehigia Ledavar Echad, when he came to
one particular הלכה, Halachah, אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru Lo Talmidav, the students
of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said to him, רבי מנין לך, Rebbi
Minayin Lach, Rebbi, where do you learn this from? אמר להן, Amar
Lahen,
he said to them, הלכה למשה מסיני. Halachah LeMoshe MiSinai. Ah, it's
a tradition going all the way back to משה. Moshe. נתיישבה דעתו,
Nityashevah Daato, now he felt better. Now he felt better because it
was all being attributed back to him. So I think, you know,
there's a fascinating discussion and I was trying to look up some
classic, you know, commentators of the אגדתא Agadeta what they did with
this, because, you know, like why, how is Rabbi Akiva different than
Moshe? Why was it given to Rabbi Akiva and not given to
Moshe? Or not given to Moshe, I mean, why was Rabbi Akiva
able to do this and not Moshe? And there were some interesting
answers to that, like for example, there was one from the משך
חכמה, Meshech Chochma, I think, that says that he tried to, when
we think of Rabbi Akiva, I think of Rabbi Akiva, like I
said, as this tremendous human creativity of תורה שבעל פה Torah She'be'al
Peh in inferring הלכות. halachos. For some reason he identified with Rabbi
Akiva in the משך חכמה, Meshech Chochma, the idea that he made
a lot of תקנות takanos and גזירות דרבנן. gezeiros derabbanan. I never
associate that with Rabbi Akiva and there are other rabbis who make
a lot of גזירות. gezeiros. Anyway, so he said that that's why
Rabbi Akiva had all of these laws, because he was making all
of these safeguards, and that, you know, that he was choosing to
express difference basically about how does one focus on one's Judaism? Does
one focus on doing the right and not so much worry about
protecting against doing the wrong, or does one focus on, you know,
protecting against the wrong? He sort of said it was between the
אנכי ה' אלהיך Anochi Hashem Elokecha versus the לא יהיה לך. Lo
yihiyeh lecha. So he said that that's why when they got to,
Moshe was the אנכי ה' אלהיך Anochi Hashem Elokecha but Rabbi Akiva...
that's how he framed it if you want, you know, sort of
the idea that rabbinic Judaism has a lot of safeguards. And then
he said that when they get to דבר אחד, davar echad, so
he says that דבר אחד davar echad is the unity of God,
אנכי ה' אלהיך, Anochi Hashem Elokecha, that ultimately he attributed back to
Moshe. Alright, there's interesting דרש, drash, but I think it takes us
far afield from what's really going on here. And what's really going
on here seems to be, you know, a powerful rabbinic acknowledgment of
the idea of תורה שבעל פה Torah She'be'al Peh and how if
somebody like משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu himself were to come down and
sit in our דף יומי Daf Yomi שיעור shiur and look at
this גמרא, Gemara, he wouldn't recognize what we were talking about because
that is the power of תורה שבעל פה, Torah She'be'al Peh, is
that we interpret and infer and that's Rabbi Akiva, קוצי קוצים של
הלכות, kotzei kotzim shel halachos, which were not necessarily the original intent,
but that's what the nature of the partnership is, is that we
are part of that process of continuing to interpret and develop to
the point that Moshe can't understand what's going on, but in the
end it all sources itself back in from Moshe, הלכה למשה מסיני,
Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, that all goes back to the Torah that Moshe
gave and that's the relationship.
And thus having said that, Moshe is satisfied. He still doesn't understand
all the דרש, drash, but he's satisfied because he knows he's the
source, the given source. And the question that was raised that you
raised was why didn't Moshe have all this and the point is
Moshe had a lot to do.
Right.
Right. Well, you know, it's like the,
it's like the parent that you know the kid doesn't know, you
know, doesn't know
his presidents and the parent says, when I was your age I
knew all of the presidents by heart at the age of six,
and the kid says, well, when you were my age there were
only three or four.
So,
so when Moshe, you didn't need a huge תורה שבעל פה Torah
She'be'al Peh yet. As time progressed you needed the תורה שבעל פה
Torah She'be'al Peh to continue to grow. Okay, so that's why נתיישבה
דעתו. nityashevah da'ato. Well, that's also what he did sometimes.
Okay, anyway, נתיישבה דעתו, nityashevah da'ato, but it was not that he
felt better because, I mean, so Rabbi Akiva was still learning all
he had to say, but he understands that it's all part of
the tradition, right, that it's not a new, it's not a different
thing, it's just a development.
Right, exactly, exactly. Okay so,
alright, so that's why God is writing these and by the way,
there's a רב
משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein in his introduction אגרות משה Igros Moshe
focuses on this גמרא Gemara and talks about the power of a
פוסק, posek, that a פוסק posek if he goes through his responsibility
correctly, you know, with real integrity and looking at all the sources
and so on, he doesn't have to be afraid that the פסק
psak is incorrect because by definition the פסק psak is correct. That's
the idea of תורה שבעל פה Torah She'be'al Peh is that you
know even if you continue to develop or whatever, if you do
it with a search for truth and with integrity and with precedence
and the sources and whatever you say ultimately will be the Torah
that God wants. And that's how he sort of says that's what's
going on here with Rabbi Akiva and Moshe. What Rabbi Akiva says
ultimately becomes God's Torah. So he says it's a beautiful, you know,
introduction to his אגרות משה, Igros Moshe, yeah.
I know this is, you know, some of this is speculation, but
don't you get the feeling that Moshe felt a sense of joy
that whatever was created at his time kept growing?
Well, he finally understood that they were ultimately acknowledging this as a
development and it was נתיישבה דעתו. nityashevah da'ato. The question is how
did he feel after נתיישבה דעתו? nityashevah da'ato? Did he make his
peace with it or was he actually happy with it? That's not
so clear.
נתיישבה דעתו nityashevah da'ato sounds a little more like made his peace
with it. Yes.
Why does it say turn around when you're looking into the future?
Yeah, so that is a
good question and especially since the whole idea is about how it
continues to develop in the future.
It could be because, you know, he goes immediately to the back
of the class. It doesn't say like he starts at the front
row and keeps on getting back moving back until he went straight
to the eighth row. So to me it's like you have to
actually take a step back. You're not Mr. Big Shot anymore, you
know, חזור לאחורך, chazor le'achorecha, like you know you have to actually
you're going to go to the back of the class and understand
that sort of in certain ways you know a lot of what
ultimately becomes authoritative is how it's interpreted after you and not ultimately.
So, that's how I would read the idea of
just saying...
Well, the idea of saying that it's תורה למשה מסיני Torah l'Moshe
mi-Sinai
when it isn't anymore.
Right? You know. Right.
But it is. But the source for that?
That's what he came up with, some that... that was. So where
do you know the source for this? I don't have a דרש
drash for the tradition. But I think the point is like Elchanan
said before,
excuse me, that even if some of it's new, but at least
like imagine משה Moshe comes in there and they're teaching a different
תורה Torah than he never heard of before. So he thinks all
his work was for nothing. But when he understands that it's the
root is his root and the... right.
No, I just had some doubts
about that one thing, but the other bit it seems that it
was.
Yeah, well, I didn't understand. I understood הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe
mi-Sinai and as this one thing of הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe
mi-Sinai but that, like, framed everything. It's all ultimately... look, it's when
we say the right of privacy, there's a constitutional right of privacy.
You know, there isn't a constitutional right of privacy. Some Supreme Court
decided that there was a constitutional right of privacy and now there's
a constitutional right of privacy. So, you know, that ultimately is... it
is תורת משה. Torat Moshe. Its authority comes from the fact that
it comes from God and it came... communicated to משה. Moshe. But
now, whatever we interpret... right. But the actual content of it...
right.
That's a very interesting paradox, right?
Yes.
Okay, well, that's the question of whether he was happy or just
נתיישבה דעתו. nityashva da'ato. But let's keep on going. So גמרא Gemara
says...
okay... where are we? Okay. חזר ובא לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. Chazar
u-va lifnei ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu. Then he returned to God. אמר לפניו,
Amar lefanav, said before him: רבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, יש
לך אדם כזה ואתה נותן תורה על ידי? yesh lecha adam kaze
ve-ata noten Torah al yadi? You have a person like this and
I'm the one you're giving the תורה Torah to? Now, of course,
the great, best answer is, "Of course, because you're actually the one
that's supposed to be the perfect vessel of just getting the words
down. We don't want your creativity, and he's the one that's going
to come later for his creativity." So, I'm serious, it's like what
Saul Lieberman said about the role of the תנאים, Tannaim, the multi-Tannaim,
the memorizers that they had for the משנה. Mishnah. They said you
wanted people with great memories and no creativity because you wanted them
just to memorize it and repeat it and not insert themselves.
But anyway, the expression comes to Judaism for exactly that.
So משה Moshe said, "So why are you giving it to me?"
So אמר לו, amar lo, שתוק, shtok, quiet. כך עלה במחשבה לפני.
kach ala be-machshava lefanai. This is my... this was my intent. This
was my game plan. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, said before him: רבונו
של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, הראיתני תורתו, hareitani Torato, הראני
שכרו. hareini secharo. Show me his תורה, Torah, show me his reward.
אמר לו, Amar lo, חזור לאחורך. chazor l'achorecha. Go back, turn around.
It's again that... there's that turn around imagery. There's got to be
something about this turning around imagery more than... more. I agree with
Rachel. Anyway, חזור לאחורך, chazor l'achorecha, he looked behind him. ראה ששוקלין
בשרו במקולין. Ra'ah she-shoklin besaro be-makulin.
He saw the Romans weighing out the meat of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva corpse in, like, the butcher stores, meaning he was martyred. You
know, they turned him into meat. So...
אמר לפניו, amar lefanav, so משה Moshe said to God: רבונו של
עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, זו תורה וזו שכרה? zu Torah ve-zu secharah?
This is the תורה Torah and this is its reward?
אמר לו, Amar lo, שתוק, shtok, quiet. כך עלה במחשבה לפני. kach
ala be-machshava lefanai.
So it was the intent before me. So again, a very interesting
parallel with the other intent. Some things are arbitrary, you can't understand.
Ultimately, it's part of the divine plan. Same way you don't understand
why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was not given the תורה, Torah, you
can't understand why this is his reward. Now, I do want to
say that this is also besides being a very powerful מדרש Midrash
about the nature of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh, it's an
extremely powerful מדרש Midrash about theodicy and about justice because so
much of Rabbinic literature is explaining how things fit into the divine
economy of reward and punishment. You know, and the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash was destroyed because of this sin, and this thing happened because
of that sin. And sometimes what's extremely powerful, especially in a post-Holocaust
era, is where the Rabbis acknowledge that this does not make any
sense within our understanding of שכר ועונש. sachar ve-onesh. And to some
point, the most honest thing we can say is we don't understand
rather than try to attribute to God a type of שכר ועונש
sachar ve-onesh which makes no sense. So that is... it's some of
that sort of, you know, within the theological issues of חז"ל Chazal
and having everything to fit. This is very powerful with the power
of acknowledging that some things just don't fit.
Yes, חזור לאחורך chazor l'achorecha is an allusion to בפרשת כי תשא
be-Parashat Ki Tissa where he can't really understand the way God acts
in
history.
משה Moshe that wanted to see God's face, and God said
ואחורי תראה.
ve-achorai tir'eh. Uh-huh. So you only get a glimpse, you don't really...
the whole... you don't have a full understanding.
Can we say that משה Moshe left history when משה Moshe was
up there with God, he stepped out of human history and so
when God says "look behind you," "look down" and... you know, you
can reintegrate
yourself into history...
right... see... you get a glimpse of human history but he at
that point left human history, he became so close to God.
Right. He
had to turn around to get... right... to get back into it.
Right. Yes, very nice.
What does the גמרא Gemara mean in the context of the earlier
where we mean... what's the message here about...
that he got the תורה Torah but also this is what happened
to him? That the... but they both have the phrase גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shaveh*? Well, I think that it's sort of it preparing us
theologically for this answer of we don't understand, it's, you know, it's
God's will, which sounds like a real punt when, you know, it's
like you're really struggling with issues of theodicy. Oh, it's all God's
will. So I think that it sort of it prepares the ground
for us by saying that there's sometimes, you know, good things that
are also we say are God's will that we don't really fully
understand. Why was Moshe זוכה *zocho* to the Torah if God could
have given it to Rabbi Akiva? So once we acknowledge that we're
not just using this as an excuse to deal with difficult theological
challenges, you know, questions of theodicy, I think that to some degree
it helps us frame, prepare us for the second answer. You know
what I'm saying?
No, right, I think so. I mean, I just, I'm going to
think about what you said, but there's a certain futility at, we
start out with every little קוץ *kotz*...
Oh, that's interesting. Oh, that's interesting. From being significant to almost haphazard
and random. Not random but haphazard. That's a
great, that's a great point. I hadn't thought about that contrast, right?
That Rabbi Akiva, no, you're right, that's great, that Rabbi Akiva has
to give meaning to everything. And in God's world or God's Torah,
even the little little crowns on the letters have significance. But ultimately
when we switch from Torah to God's world, some things just don't
make any sense, at least to our understanding. That, that's a very
powerful point. But again, I'm not sure what the larger message is.
That's a very powerful point, but in the text here...
Right. It even makes it more prickly, you know?
So, but maybe that's again the power
of
תורה Torah שבעל פה *Torah she-ba'al peh*, meaning we really are as
human beings, we really can't understand God, and we really can't understand
how the world makes sense, you know, from, you know, how do
we really fully see God in the world? Why do some people
get things they don't deserve? Why do some people get punished? You
know, that whole thing. So when we really sort of think, we
really, it would be, it would be arrogant to think we can
understand how God works in the world. But תורה שבעל פה *Torah
she-ba'al peh*, we're given the license to go ahead and interpret, you
know, make order of it, interpret everything. And that's sort of how
God has brought us in, you know, through interpreting the Torah, not
through interpreting the world.
But then we should make, do things that make sense to human
beings. Right. Not to God.
Well, that, that is a lot of what the תורה שבעל פה
*Torah she-ba'al peh* is about. You know, since obviously God did not
intend all of these תילי תילים *tilli tillim* because the, the crowns
are arbitrary, right? So we are interpreting it, you know, very much
from sort of our human perspective and our desire to derive הלכה
halacha. *halacha*. But I like it. I mean your point about the
complete contrast about, you know, no ability to give order in the
world and then give, you know, you know, so immense order or
meaning in every little letter. But maybe that's exactly the point, but
that's a beautiful idea. Okay. So now,
alright, now to continue. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, שבע אותיות צריכות שלשה
זיונין *sheva otiyot tzrichot sheloshah ziyunin*. Now that we have that wonderful
מדרש *Midrash*, now we're going to talk about הלכה halacha? *halacha*. שבע
אותיות צריכות שלשה זיונין *sheva otiyot tzrichot sheloshah ziyunin*. The seven letters
require these three little like crowns, ornaments. ואלו הן *ve-eilu hen*, שעטנז
גץ Shatnez Get *Shatnez Getz*. The ש, ע, ט, נ, ז, ג,
צ *shin, ayin, tet, nun, zayin, gimmel, tzadi*. And that's, I gave
you that sampling of text. אמר רב amar Rav אשי *Amar Rav
Ashi*, חזינא להו לספרי דוקני דבי רב Rav *hazina lehu le-sifrei dukni
de-vei Rav*. I've seen these very precise ספרים sefarim. *sefarim* in the
house of Rav. דחטרי להו לגגיה דחית *de-chatri lehu le-gageih de-chet*. They
made a, they made a bump in the, in the top of
the חית *chet*. And what does that bump mean? If you look
at רש"י *Rashi*, he says it's sort of like the קוצו של
יוד kotzo shel yud *kotzo shel yod* that we were talking about.
It's the little fact that it, that a little thing rises, you
see the חית *chet* in רש"י *Rashi*, that there's a little bit
of a pointy thing that comes up at the top of the
left. Okay, you see that in the רש"י *Rashi*? Okay. Okay, so
that's what he said. But תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says no, חוטרי *chatri*
is like a, a, what do you call it? Like a hump
of a camel. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* based on another גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has that a חית *chet* is supposed to look like two
זינין *zayinin* connected with a camel hump. Okay, and that's that picture
in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*. So that's what חוטרא *chutra* is, it's a
camel hump. If you look at your חית *chet* here in the
picture, you see we follow תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*. If you look at
the sampling of the writing, right, it's done subtly, it's obviously in
תוספות *Tosafot*. So take a look at the חית *chet*. You see
how if you would remove the hump you'd get two זינין *zayinin*,
right? You see that in the sampling I handed out? Okay.
So anyway, just looking at a Torah.
Well, the, I think the keyword here is ספרי דוקני *sifrei dukni*,
very precise ones. Some were written with greater precision and greater care,
and others were written a little more sloppily. Okay. So it's actually
saying here better, so I looked at the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
*Sefer Torah*, but I looked at a good one. I looked at
one that was very precise.
Okay. Okay, so it had a little bump in the חית *chet*.
דתלו לכרעיה דה"א *de-talu le-chareih de-heh*, and it suspended the leg of
the ה"א Heh? *heh*, meaning the leg of the ה"א Heh *heh*,
the left leg, you don't want it to touch to the roof
or else it's going to be a חית *chet* not a ה"א
Heh, *heh*. So it has to be suspended in mid-air. Okay. חטרי
להו לגגיה דחית *chatri lehu le-gageih de-chet*, it made a hump in
the top of the חית *chet*, כמאמר חי הוא ברומו של עולם
*ke-mo amar chai hu be-rumo shel olam*, to point up to God,
you know, especially if you have like the little triangle like תוספות
*Tosafot*. God lives up in the high. And the word
חית *chet* is like... It suspended the leg of the ה, hey.
the left leg, כדבעי מיניה רב יהודה נשיאה מרב אמי. kidebay minei
Rav Yehuda Nesi'a mi-Rav Ami. So we were going to ask about
the significance of the... of the picture of the ה. hey Now
the funny thing is that presumably if you make a ח chet
without the little bump it's still כשר. kosher. We don't know that
but we can imagine that that could be true. But if you
don't if your leg of the ה hey, is connected to the
top it's no longer a ה, hey now a ח. chet. So
the differences here are not necessarily of the same weight. But anyway
why is the leg of the ה hey. suspended?
Like the question was asked of רב יהודה נשיאה Rav Yehuda Nesi'a
from רב אמי. Rav Ami. מאי דכתיב, Mai dikesiv, what meant by
the verse, בטחו בהשם עדי עד, Bitchu ba-Hashem adei ad, trust in
God forever and ever, כי ביה השם צור עולמים, ki be-kah Hashem
tzur olamim, because in יה, Kah, one of God's name, God is
the rock of... of the world. So what does that mean ביה,
be-kah, with... with the name יה? Kah? So אמר ליה, amar leh,
כה תולו בקונה הקדוש ברוך הוא, ko atolu bi-kono Hakadosh Baruch Hu,
so he didn't understand the question. He just said what's פשט pshat
in the פסוק. pasuk. What did the פסוק pasuk say? Trust in
God. He says okay, כה תולו בקונה הקדוש ברוך הוא, ko atolu
bi-kono Hakadosh Baruch Hu, she put your faith in God, הרי הוא
לו מחסה בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא. harei hu lo machseh ba-olam hazeh
u-va-olam haba. צור, עולמים, tzur olamim. maybe he thought the question was
the plural of worlds. So God will be there, will be your
safeguard, will be there for you in this world and in the
world to come. So that's what he thought he was asking him.
What's פשט pshat in the פסוק. pasuk. So
אמר ליה, amar leh, no no no, that wasn't my question. אנא
הכי קקשיא לי, Ana hachi ka-kasha li, here was my question. מאי
שנא דכתיב ביה? Mai shena dikesiv be-kah? It says because in יה
Kah God is צור Tzur, עולמים. olamim, What's the ב? beis? ולא
כתיב יה? Ve-lo kesiv Kah? Why doesn't it just say יה? Kah?
Why does it say trust in God because God is the rock
of ages? What's the ב, be, with יה? Kah? So he says
ah, כדרש רב יהודה בר רב אלעאי. kiderash Rav Yehuda bar Rav
Ilai. רב יהודה בר אלעאי Rav Yehuda bar Ilai interprets: אלו שני
עולמות. elu shenei olamot. The יה Kah is the י yud and
the ה. hey So it's not saying God, it's saying with י
yud and ה hey. השם צור עולמים. Hashem tzur olamim. God fashioned
the world through the use of the two letters of His name,
the י yud and the ה. hey. So how is this? אלו
שני עולמות שברא הקדוש ברוך הוא, Elu shenei olamot she-bara Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, אחד בה ואחד בי. echad be-hey ve-echad be-yud. ואיני יודע אם
עולם הבא בי ועולם הזה בה, Ve-ini yodea im olam haba be-yud
ve-olam hazeh be-hey, was it the
future world was with the י yud and this world with the
ה. hey. By the way again remember that in traditional חזל, Chazal,
future world is not where your soul goes after you die, future
world is what happens after משיח Mashiach comes, what this world will
be in the future times. Okay, so I don't know if that
world was created with the י yud and our world with the
ה. hey. אם עולם הזה בי ועולם הבא בה, Im olam hazeh
be-yud ve-olam haba be-hey, or this world was with י yud and
the future world was with the ה. hey כשהוא אומר אלה תולדות
השמים והארץ בהבראם, Keshe-hu omer eileh toldot hashamayim ve-ha'aretz be-hibaram, these are
the stories of the heavens and the earth when they were created,
right right at the beginning of בראשית. Bereishit. So the ה hey.
in בהבראם be-hibaram when God created them is small and therefore the
דרשא drasha is: אל תקרי בהבראם, al tikrei be-hibaram, in their creating,
אלא בה בראם, ella be-hey bera'am, God created them with the letter
ה. hey, בה בראם. Be-hey bera'am. So this world was created in
the ה, hey, the future world would be with the י. yud.
הרי הוא אומר עולם הזה בה, Harei hu omer olam hazeh be-hey,
this world was created with the ה, hey? ועולם הבא בי, ve-olam
haba be-yud, and the future world in the י. yud. ומפני מה,
U-mi-pnei mah, so now what's the meaning of all this? נברא עולם
הזה בה? Nivra olam hazeh be-hey? Why is this world created with
the ה? hey What's the symbolism of that?
מפני שדומה לאכסדרה,
Mi-pnei
she-domeh
le-achsaderah, a ה hey is like a courtyard, a portico. אמי, Omi,
what? Yes. So a ה hey has like three walls right? And
it's open on the fourth wall, like they would have a portico
which you enter into a house. You first have the... we mentioned
that before, this
אכסדרה. achsaderah. שכל הרוצה לצאת יצא. She-kol ha-rotzeh latzet yetze. But of
course now viewing it as the exit door, which is anybody that's
not interested in really making, you know, trying to toil in this
world and wants to instead just you know, quickly get to גיהנום
Gehennom essentially, the point here. You know and not so... okay, there's
a big door on the bottom for anybody, it's like a big
trap door for anybody who wants to leave, be my guest. Go
ahead and leave. Okay you can go ahead and waste your world
if you want to. Okay however, ומאי טעמא תליא כרעיה? u-mai ta'ama
talia kara'ei? And why though is the little leg of the ה
hey suspended? דהדר
בתשובה, De-hadar bi-teshuvah,
if you want to enter back into this world, you want to
do תשובה teshuvah and really make a serious go of things in
terms of your role in this world, מעיילי, mayilei, you can sneak
back through the back door. Okay, so we've got a big open
door policy except the open door policy is really an open exit
door policy. Okay, we're not going to stop anybody that wants to
waste their life, the door's open, be my guest, leave. Okay but
there's a back door is that you can come back in if
you do תשובה. teshuvah. It's real small though you have to work
a little harder, you have to maybe climb up the leg of
ה to get back in. But there's a back door to come
back in. Okay. ולא עיילי בהך? Ve-la ayeili be-hah? So why not
go back through that big open door you left? דלא מסתייעא מילתא.
De-lo mistaya milta.
Things won't work out so well if you try to retrace your
footsteps. Okay. ריש לקיש, Reish Luggiz, ריש
לקיש Reish Luggiz says, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says: מאי דכתיב, mai dikesiv,
what meant by the verse:
אם ללצים הוא יליץ, im laleitzim hu yalitz, if one is for
mockers
God will
if you're humble and you're trying to do the right thing, מסייעין
אותו, Mesayi'in Oto, God will help you out. בא לטמא, Ba Letamei,
if however you're trying to do the wrong thing and you're coming
to impure yourself, פותחין לו, Potchin Lo, God's not literally going to
help you do the wrong thing but he's not going to close
the door. You want it? The door's open. You want to go
do something wrong, be my guest. Okay, he's not going to stand
in your way. Now what does it have to do about going
back to the same הא? Heh So Rashi says here, where's Rashi?
מסייעין אותו על מה בא לסייע. Mesayi'in Oto Al Mah Ba Lesayaye.
So Rashi just gives
an indirect proof that if God needs to help you when you're
doing the right thing, so you're not just going back through the
same door you came, you gotta climb up that harder ladder to
get into that back door if it requires help. But presumably the
point also is, you know, it's a psychological point, which is if
you really want to start changing your behaviors, it's not just putting
yourself back into the exact same scenarios you had been in before
and just say, oh by force of will I'm going to make
everything better and now. If you really want to have another serious
go about it, you have to find a new way to approach
things and that's the whole idea. But that needs help because it's
hard, right? It's hard to start things afresh and approach things from
a whole new way, and that's the, you know, מסייעין אותו, Mesayi'in
Oto, you need God's help. Okay. So, ומאי טעמא אית ליה תגא?
Umai Ta'ama It Lei Taga? And now why
does the הא Heh have a little תגא, Taga, have a little
like crown? Now it's not the שעטנז גץ because it's not those
are the big crowns, but this is a little thing.
Okay, תוגיים? Tugayim? Look at Tosafot, it points to the קוץ של
יוד. Kotz Shel Yod. We've had the קוץ של יוד, Kotz Shel
Yod, the קוץ של חית, Kotz Shel Chet, now we have the
קוץ של הא, Kotz Shel Heh, right? At the top left, a
little point goes up. Why is that there? ומאי טעמא אית ליה
תגא? Umai Ta'ama It Lei Taga? Amar Rabbi Berachya, God says, אם
חוזר בו, Im Chozer Bo, if this person is doing תשובה Teshuva
and trying to get back into the top door, אני קושר לו
קשר. Ani Kosher Lo Kesher. I will throw him a rope. Okay,
meaning I'll tie a knot. So it could be like he's giving
you a little crown, but I imagine it more like you have
to scale, you know, the wall there and get to get into
that door, so God's sort of reaching out his hand and throwing
you the rope to help you scale up to get back into
that little into that little door.
Okay. So, again you have God tying the knot, but what's not
the knot of the crowns from before?
Okay.
ומפני מה? Umipnei Mah? But look at the side of the גירסא,
Girsa, it
says, אני קושר לו כתר. Ani Kosher Lo Keter. Do you see
at that little
left hand column? Some replaced the word קשר Kesher with the word
כתר, Keter, a crown, which is exactly back to God tying the
crowns on the letter and it's sort of like I'll give them
status, acknowledgment, reward, and so on. ומפני מה נברא עולם הבא ביו"ד?
Umipnei Mah Nivra Olam Haba BeYod? And why is the future world
with a יוד? Yod? מפני שהצדיקים שבו מועטין. Mipnei ShehaTzadikim Shebo Muatin.
Because the future world is going to be a lot less populated
than this world. It's a tiny little יוד. Yod. Okay, there are
not many people will be of the future world, there'll be a
much, so the numbers will be smaller.
ומפני מה כפוף ראשו? Umipnei Mah Kafuf Rosho? And why is the
head like a little bit bent in the יוד? Yod? I'm not
exactly sure, but I mean if you imagine that most of it
is bent, if you imagine it looks like a person, right? So
most letters the weight is on the bottom and they have some
head, but the יוד Yod is like the whole thing like it's
a little leg and the whole thing is bent over. Yeah, basically.
So why does it look like that? מפני שהצדיקים שבו כפופים ראשיהם.
Mipnei ShehaTzadikim Shebo Kfufim Rasheihem.
Because their heads are bent over, they're humble. Okay, not only humble,
they also don't want to be jealous. מפני מעשיהם שאינם דומים זה
לזה. Mipnei Ma'aseihem She'einam Domim Zeh Lazeh.
Their actions are not similar to one another. What Rashi says means
that like if you look at Rashi here, וכבודו של צדיק מרובה
משל חברו משום הכי ראשיהם כפופים דמתבייש מחברו,
Ukevodo Shel Tzadik Merubeh Meshel Chaveiro Mishum Hachi
Rasheihem Kfufim Demitbayesh Mechaveiro,
that even if everybody is צדיקים, Tzadikim, there's some greater צדיקים Tzadikim
and lesser צדיקים, Tzadikim, and so you don't want to be shamed
because you're humble, rather than being arrogant that you're one of the
few people that made it to עולם הבא Olam Haba and you're
one of the צדיקים, Tzadikim, right? You actually are ashamed like look
at that guy, look how much more he accomplished than I did,
and you're going to be embarrassed. So because of that, you look
down. Yeah.
Wait, I missed it.
What do you mean created the worlds as a letter?
It means that the symbolism of the letter, the, okay, on the
one hand because these יוד Yod and the הא, and you did
miss it, I didn't really say it. The יוד Yod and the
הא are letters of God's name, so it basically means, I think,
means that just as God is a creator, but it speaks to
sort of God's immanence in the world. Like the very world is
created by God's name. So first of all, that's one of the
messages. But then the specific use of the letter is the sense
about like how does, what are the metaphysical realities upon which the
world operates?
So if the world is created with the הא of God's name,
then the metaphysical reality that this world operates in is it's easy
to throw your life away, but there's always an opportunity for תשובה,
Teshuva, but it requires effort. And the metaphysical reality of the world
to come is that it's a lot harder to
get in, you know, it's a much smaller space and that's something
that requires much more achievements in order to go there. But you're
right, I
did... Okay, so, okay, אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, הני תרי
מילי
hanni trei
milli
אמר רב Rav, בדברים דתניא תיובתא. bidvarim detanya tiuvta.
So after that amazing, you know, מדרשים, midrashim, now we get back
to some hard hard nuts and bolts הלכה. halacha Okay, so the
following two things רב Rav, said relating to דברי תורה, divrei Torah,
and we taught a ברייתא braita that is a contradiction. חדא דהא
Chada deha דאמר רב, deamar Rav, ספר תורה שיש בו שתי טעויות
בכל דף ודף יתקן. Sefer Torah sheyesh bo shtei tauyot bechol daf
v'daf yitaken.
If a ספר תורה Sefer Torah has two mistakes at in every
column, a דף daf here does not mean a what do you
call it, a full page, that's called a יריעה, yeriah, the entire
קלפים klafim that you know are sewn together, but a דף daf
here means a column. עמוד, Amud, we know we normally call an
עמוד amud a column. We have an עמוד א׳ amud aleph and
an עמוד ב׳. amud beis. But factually and technically, an עמוד amud
does not mean the side of the page, it means literally a
column, like an עמוד amud is a column of a building, which
is why in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, for example, you have when people
are giving you know where something is located in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
the traditional printing of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, they will say א׳, ב׳,
ג׳, או ד׳. aleph, beis, gimmel, or daled. What the heck is
עמוד ג׳ amud gimmel or ד׳? daled? Do they have like a
you know a rectangle rectangle of something? No, because it was printed
with two columns on side א׳ aleph and two columns on side
ב׳. beis. So עמוד amud actually means a column. In this context,
דף daf also means a column. Okay, so if your ספר תורה
Sefer Torah has three has he said has three two errors in
every column, then you can still fix it. However, if it's כל
כך, kol kach, so you know poorly done that it has שלש,
shalosh, three errors in every column, then it is then יגנז. yiganeiz.
Put it in שמות, shemos, it's not worth it to take out
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah that has that many corrections in it.
דתניא תיובתא, Detanya tiuvta, we taught a contradiction that a ברייתא braita
same idea but goes but is a little more lenient. שלש יתקן,
Shalosh yitaken, three mistakes in every column you can fix, ארבע יגנז,
arba yiganeiz, four mistakes in every column you have to put it
in שמות. shemos. תנא, Tana, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, אם
יש בו דף אחת שלימה מטרת על כולה. im yesh bo daf
achat shleima materet al kula. However, if you have one perfect column,
okay, that has no mistakes, it can you know it can go
a long way. It can make oh it's not like this is
a terribly a completely terrible ספר תורה Sefer Torah. to to put
in שמות shemos we'll buy into it. No, if one is good,
then we can more tolerate some of the other problems and fix
them. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara... is of course going to be
how perfect does the perfect one have to be?
Yeah, that is a continuing our central theme of מעכב. me'akeiv.
Oh that's an interesting point. I don't think so, because מעכב me'akeiv
actually means if something is wrong can you just go on without
it? Right here you're actually fixing it, so the question is more
like how much is it just such a problem that even if
you fixed it we don't it's like you know it's I don't
think it's exactly the מעכב. me'akeiv. מעכב Me'akeiv is you don't have
it, it's still good. Here you are going to fix it, but
maybe it's not good anyway because it just was so filled with
mistakes, you know.
Okay, so now the גמרא...
Gemara Yeah, so
the צדיק tzaddik in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, you know, maybe there
are people greater than him, maybe you know he has many flaws
also but
that one good thing about him, one good דף, daf, that's how
he's deemed.
Ah
very nice. So even if you have a lot of things that
need fixing in the rest of you, there's one area of your
life that's beautiful. I think we got people I think we brought
people's need רש״י Rashi to this.
Okay, זה איש מברייא, zeh ish meverya, alrighty exactly, absolutely true.
אמר רב יצחק בר שמואל, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel, רב יהודה
בר שמואל Rav Yehuda bar Shmuel said, okay got we got to
get a little make a little more distance here. בר משמיה דרב
Bar mashmeih deRav in the name of רב, Rav?
והוא דכתיב רוביה דספרא שפיר.
vehu dechtiv rubya desifra
shapir.
When do we say that you can tolerate these mistakes or one
will save the rest? If most of the ספר Sefer is written
correctly. Now what does it mean if most of the ספר Sefer
is written correctly? Most of the ספר Sefer written correctly, then it's
not true that you've got mistakes on every single column.
So one minute.
I have to check this up beforehand. The ראש Rosh does says
he understands this.
One second. I'm checking. You know what, let's go on.
I'm trying to
remember.
The ראש Rosh has a discussion about this. What does it matter?
You know how do you basically say both things? If it's mistakes
in every single column then you can't have רוב rov of the
ספר Sefer written correctly.
Unless it's saying that you need both. That רוב rov needs to
be
correct and then even in the then it's the minority of all
the minority every one of the minority has a mistake.
Okay. But it's obviously hemming it in even more. Alright, let's keep
on going and it says like this: או איבעיא להו לרב יוסף
o ibeiya lehu leRav Yosef איבעיא להו לרב יוסף ibeiya lehu leRav
Yosef אי בהוא דף שלוש טעויות מאי. i behu daf shalosh ta'uyot
mai. Let's say that one column that was perfect that saved everything
else, that itself has three errors, okay, three errors you're allowed to
fix. So it's not perfect. It's just not hitting the four problem.
So what's the הלכה? אמר להו הואיל ואיסתרו ויתקונין מתקי. amar leh
hovil u'sterai v'tikunin mitakei.
Since it was, didn't, was under four, it was three, and it
allowed, it's the number that you're allowed to fix, you're allowed to
fix up to three, then it is considered to save the whole
rest of the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah Okay, so we are on
the one hand being stricter that you need רוב rov of the
ספר sefer to be written correctly, to be written without mistakes, but
we're also being a little bit more lenient that this one column
that saves the rest doesn't have to be completely perfect, but it
can have as long as it has no more than three mistakes.
And now we go on: והני מילי דחסרי v'hanei milei d'chasrei והני
מילי דחסרי רוב. v'hanei milei d'chasrei rov. And when are the problems?
When the problems are that letters are lacking, because if you're lacking
a letter, what do you have to do to fix it? You
have to scrape away the whole word and rewrite the word again
in smaller letters. That's a big
fixing. אבל יתירות aval yoteirot אבל יתירות לית לן בה, aval yoteirot
lait lan bah, it's not a problem. Which does not mean תוספות
says that you don't have to worry about extra letters, but it
just means you're not doing as radical of a fix. Scraping away
an extra letter is not going to look as bad as scraping
away the whole thing. I have to say that the way they
write the ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, and I'm familiar with this now
because we hire a סופר sofer regularly to write the קלפים k'laphim
for our students,
you can't tell that they have, you know, I'll see a problem
and I'll tell him you got this word totally wrong, and I'm
saying to myself, how's he going to wheeze in the extra יוד,
yud, how's it going to look so sloppy if he does it?
You can never tell that the thing was scraped away and corrected
because the way they use the ink on the, the type of
ink they use, the parchment that they use, you can scrape it
away and it's like it's completely invisible. You don't even see that
something had been written on it. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara, I
think was concerned that there would be some type of marks left
and therefore the marks are much greater if you have to scrape
away the whole word and fit in a missing letter than if
you just have to scrape away an extra letter.
Okay, so אבל יתירות אבל חסירות מאי טעמא לאו, aval yoteirot aval
chaseras mai ta'ama lav, and what's the problem if what do you
call it
if letters or words were missing? Because אמר רב כהנא
משום דמיחזי כמנומר, amar Rav Kahana mishum d'michezi k'menumar, it looks like
a leopard. They were spotted. So if you're going to have to
do a lot of scrapings away and three or four fixes on
every single column and it's not just fitting in, you know, taking
away an extra letter, scraping away the whole word and writing the
word again, then that's going to really be a not appropriate ספר
תורה Sefer Torah and therefore you should just put the whole thing
in גניזה. genizah. Today we're going to continue with this, but I
did want to say one other point by the way that I
forgot to mention and it really refers to you had spoken about
this קוצו של יוד kotzo shel yud, story, right? Are these issues
of the letters a similar issue when you're dealing with not ספרי
תורה, Sifrei Torah, תפילין Tefillin and מזוזות? Mezuzot? I mean the context
sounds very highly, once you know, a highly ritualized ספרים. So if
you look at this little תוספות on כט עמוד ב, chaf-tet amud
bet, דאייתי ינוקא דלא חכים ולא טיפש, de'il ayei yenuka d'la chacham
v'la tipesh,
he says like this, the first תוספות on כט עמוד ב, chaf-tet
amud bet,
מעשה היה בגט שהיה דלת שדומה קצת ליו''ד. ma'aseh hayah be-get shehayah
dalet shedomah k'tzat l'yud.
The דלת dalet almost looked like a
יוד. yud. Okay, so would you have to use a קטן, katan,
would you have to identify it as a דלת dalet as opposed
to יוד? yud?
So it says והביאו ר' אליהו ינוקא דלא חכים ולא טיפש וקרא
בו כדת, v'hevi Rav Eliyahu yenuka d'la chacham v'la tipesh v'kara bo
k'da'at, so they brought this minor to read it and he read
it correctly, he didn't just identify the letter, he read it in
context, he read the whole word כדת. k'da'at. Okay, והכשירו מהך דשמעתא,
v'hishiru me'hach d'shmayta,
and he said it was kosher based on this גמרא, Gemara which
basically seems to say that you need to follow the same rules.
But again remember that's where the problem was the basic shape of
the word, is it a יוד yud or is it a דלת?
dalet? If like the other rules like מוקף גויל, mukaf gvil, קוצו
של יוד, that's not so clear and that's you know interesting what
exactly.
Do it again, it's what I was saying they go crazy and
of course, and this holds up specifically as he's sitting and they're
buying a גט get and everything in front of the סופר. sofer.
I can imagine now.
Okay, so now last line of כט עמוד ב, chaf-tet amud bet,
איגרא חמוה דרבי אבא, igra chamucheh d'Rav Abba, Igra the father-in-law of
רבי אבא, Rav Abba, הוה ליה יתירות בסיפריה, hava lei yoteirot b'sifreih,
he had extra letters in his ספר, sefer, which we talked before
not a big deal, scrape it away it doesn't make the ספר
sefer look too bad. אתא לקמיה דרבי אבא, ata l'kameih d'Rav Abba,
he came to רבי אבא Rav Abba his son-in-law, אמר ליה, amar
leh, so רבי אבא Rav Abba said: Don't worry about it. לא
אמרן אלא בחסירות. lo amarnan ela b'chaseras. When do we say having
a lot of mistakes is a problem and we won't even let
you fix it? If it is things word letters are missing because
then you have to scrape, do a lot of scraping. אבל יתירות,
aval yoteirot, in your case even presumably if there were a lot
of extra letters or a lot of it was throughout the ספר,
sefer, לית לן בה, leit lan bah, it is not a big
deal, we allow for corrections, it doesn't look so bad. תוספות says
some people mistakenly think this גמרא Gemara means you don't have to
correct it if it's an extra letter. That's not what it's saying.
It's saying we can correct it, but we don't have to worry
that we have to do
a
lot.
Yeah, here the assumption is is that we're using it only in
a ritual context. Now there is a concern in הלכה even if
you only want to use it for studying, are we concerned that
if it's not מוגה mugah and it's not correctly, you know, corrected,
that you might accidentally come to use it for a ritual context?
But the assumption here is you want to use it for ritual
context. Okay, yeah. All right, so now we have ten minutes to
do today's דף. daf. All right.
We'll stay till tomorrow before we start.
When is it? Between מנחה mincha and מעריב, maariv, yeah. Okay, unless
we want to do it twice because we are really close to
a דף daf behind. Is anybody up for that? Like before מנחה
mincha maybe, between מנחה mincha and מעריב? maariv? Why don't we do
that? Because we're really, I mean, we're almost a full דף daf
behind, we might as well make it up.
Or we have to poll?
I'll poll them. Oh, you'll take care of it? Okay, fine. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אידך דאמר רב, idach d’amar
Rav, so that was one teaching of רב, Rav which was three
or four mistakes in every single column. What was the other teaching
of רב? Rav, That רב Rav said by ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah,
הכותב ספר תורה בא לגמור גומר ואפילו באמצע הדף. Hakoteiv Sefer Torah
ba ligmor gomeir va’afilu b’emtza hadaf. When you're writing your ספר תורה
Sefer Torah
and you come to the last פסוק, pasuk, okay, you know סופרים,
Sofrim, not only do they have to do the individual writing correctly,
they've got to plan well in advance because they need the
לעיני כל ישראל L’einei chol Yisrael to be at the bottom of
a column. Not only that, there are some things like the שירת
הים Shirat HaYam and האזינו Ha’azinu that you have to get them,
you know, exact and start them in a particular place in the
column. So you have to plan in advance. So he's saying, well
what if you didn't plan in advance? And here you are, you
got to לעיני כל ישראל L’einei chol Yisrael and you're at the
top of a column. Are you allowed to end a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah at the top of a column? So he said yes,
וגומר ואפילו באמצע הדף, v’gomeir va’afilu b’emtza hadaf, you can end even
in the middle of a column.
מיתיבי, Meisivei, we ask against it, we have a
ברייתא Braisa from
מסכת סופרים, Masechet Sofrim, הכותב ספר תורה בא לגמור לא יגמור באמצע
הדף... Hakoteiv Sefer Torah ba ligmor lo yigmor b’emtza hadaf... כדרך שגומר
בחומשין, k’derech shegomeir b’Chumashin, like you would do in a חומש. Chumash.
A חומש, Chumash, by the way, in the time before the printing
press was basically a codex. It was like scribed on parchment, but
it was random access. You know, I mean, that's the problem with
the scroll, you got to... like when we used to have cassette
tapes as opposed to CD-ROMs, right? So what they would do is
they would bind it into a book, but it would still be
scribed. Actually, where they had that amazing, you know, thing, when was
that? The guy filming the
library... whatever, anyway, you could see these gorgeous, you know, codices which
were scribed and the כתב ksav was beautiful and was on קלף,
klaf, but it was made as a codex, made as a bound
book. Okay, so that was חומשין. Chumashin. They could not be used,
you know, obviously for ritual purposes. There actually is a position of
the רמב"ם Rambam that says that if you don't have a ספר
תורה Sefer Torah. you can read from a חומש, Chumash, that type
of a חומש Chumash at least in שול. shul. That it's only
a כבוד ציבור k’vod tzibbur issue and if there's no option you
can even read from at least a handwritten חומש Chumash in the
שול. shul. Anyway, so presumably when you ended a חומש, Chumash, you
didn't have to end at the end of a column, you would
end wherever you would end. So it says maybe you could do
the same when you're writing a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah,
לא יגמור באמצע הדף כדרך שגומר בחומשין, lo yigmor b’emtza hadaf k’derech
shegomeir b’Chumashin, do not end in the middle of a column, אלא
מקצר והולך עד סוף הדף, ela mekatzeir v’holeich ad sof hadaf, you
have to get to the end of the column even if it
means that your lines will slowly get shorter and shorter and shorter,
but you have to get to the bottom and you have a
nice little קוץ וריש. kotz v’reish. Okay, now of course that means
that you have enough lines left. If you if you would have
ended in the middle, plan from the beginning and eventually you can
get to the bottom. But if you would have ended in three
lines at the top, you're not going to anyway get to the
bottom. So you got to really plan in advance.
Very long letters, right.
Well, we're going to get, we're going to actually get to that
possibility in a minute. Okay, so anyway, this is a contradiction of
רב, Rav so the גמרא says, because רב Rav says you can
end in the middle, כי קאמר רב דחומשים. ki ka’amar Rav d’chumashim.
When רב Rav said end in the middle, he meant a חומש.
Chumash. Now of course that's already funny, since when would there be
ritual laws of a חומש? Chumash?
But this shows you that when you're writing it on קלף klaf
and especially according to the רמב"ם Rambam that things you could read
from חומשים Chumashim and חומשים Chumashim have
קדושה, kedusha, you know, when the תורה talks about stacking books and
so on when it's written, handwritten on קלף, klaf, it had a
certain, you know, religious weight even if it wasn't used in the
שול. shul. So there could actually be rules of how do you
write in חומשין. Chumashin.
They
copied the... they wrote a new book? They copied the old? Right.
So you didn't necessarily have to copy from a valid ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, oh that's interesting.
We actually פוסקים pasken that you do copy from a valid ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah... but whether that would have been strictly necessary is
a good point. Right. Okay, so anyway, so when did רב say
you could end in the middle of a column? By a חומש.
Chumash. הגמרא Hagemara says, אה ספר תורה קאמר.
Ah,
Sefer Torah ka’amar.
רב says if you're writing a ספר sefer תורה... so it says
okay, חומשים של ספר תורה, chumashim shel Sefer Torah, which means the
חמישי חומשי תורה. chamishai chumshei Torah. When you end בראשית, Bereishis, you
don't have to end it at the bottom of a column. And
if you know, we don't do that. We end בראשית Bereishis wherever
we end it, we have four blank lines and then we start
שמות. Shmos. And we end שמות Shmos wherever we end it and
we have four blank lines and we start ויקרא. Vayikra. So when
you come to end one ספר of the חמישה ספרים chamisha sfarim
of the ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, you can end in the middle
of a column. Okay. Okay. אין *In*? Is it true? אמר רב
יהושע בר אבא *Amar Rav Yehoshua bar Abba*, אמר רב גידל *Amar
Rav Giddel*, אמר רב *Amar Rav*, לעיני כל ישראל *Le'einei Kol Yisrael*
באמצע הדף *be'emtza hadaf*? That's pretty explicit. You can have the word
לעיני כל ישראל *Le'einei Kol Yisrael* in the middle of a column,
which sounds like the original teaching of רב *Rav*, you don't have
to go to the bottom of the column. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says תהי באמצע שיטה איתמר *Tahi be'emtza shita itmar*. He did not
mean, although that's not what he says, he didn't mean the middle
of a column, he meant the middle of a line. You have
to end it at the bottom of the column, but you don't
have to end it at the end of the line. You know,
as when you write actually a כתובה *Kesuvah*, right, you know at
the bottom it's like, you know, הכל שריר וקיים *Hakol Sharir Ve'kayam*,
those three words can take up this much space 'cause you want
to have it like right and left justified, end at the end
of the line. So here it's saying you don't have to do
that. לעיני כל ישראל *Le'einei Kol Yisrael* can end at the middle
of a line, but it has to be at the bottom of
a column. Okay, now the גמרא *Gemara* is going to quote a
debate about that.
איתמר *Itmar*, רבנן
אמרי *Rabbanan amri* אף באמצע שיטה *af be'emtza shita*, it can end
even in the middle of a line, which presumably means not only
in the middle of a column, but even in the middle of
a line. רב אשי אמר *Rav Ashi amar* באמצע שיטה דווקא *be'emtza
shita davka*. No, only in the middle of a line, that's okay,
but it has to end at the bottom of a column. This
is all really about the aesthetics, right, it's to look nice, the
last
thing
has to go to the bottom. Maybe you say don't, you know,
the line doesn't have to be left justified, but the column has
to go to the bottom. רב אשי אמר *Rav Ashi amar*, okay,
והלכתא *vehilchesa* and the הלכה *halacha* is באמצע שיטה דווקא *be'emtza shita
davka*. We allow you to end in the middle of a sentence,
לעיני כל ישראל *Le'einei Kol Yisrael*, but we do not allow you
to end in the middle of a column, and you have to
plan ahead to get the last end of the ספר תורה *Sefer
Torah* to be at the bottom of the column. And later we're
going to talk about what happens if you have to write really
big letters in order to make that happen.
Okay, so we will end here for today. Good
luck.